<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></title>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-14T20:40:00+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://shan.tanu.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sh@tanu.me]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ab-Soul's Outro by Kendrick Lamar]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/14/ab-souls-outro-by-kendrick-lamar/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-14T20:26:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/14/ab-souls-outro-by-kendrick-lamar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe width="420" height="315"
src="http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/gtUsEbbVBuo?rel=0" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>&#8220;Ab-Soul&#8217;s Outro&#8221; from <em>Section 80</em> by Kendrick Lamar is a great example of
what rap music can accomplish.</p>

<p>Jazz has had an influence on rap even before NWA started <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N.W.A#Influence">sampling jazz tunes in their beats</a>.
Improvisation is a key characteristic of jazz, and it also happens to be a key
part of the creative process for rap music. Unlike conventional poetry, rap
music aims to bend words to create a unique flow like jazz.</p>

<p>In &#8220;Ab-Soul&#8217;s Outro,&#8221; Kendrick Lamar and Ab-Soul acknowledge that influence by
featuring jazz prominently in the track itself. The producer of the song,
Terrace Martin, is also an excellent saxophonist who is featured throughout the
song and has a solo at the end of the track.</p>

<p>More than anything, these lines keep repeating in my head:</p>

<blockquote><p>What&#8217;s your life about? Enlighten me.
Is you gonna live on your knees or die on your feet?
Is you gonna plead the fifth or sound the horn?
The time is now, child come on.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creativity is Often Just About Showing Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/10/creativity-is-often-just-about-showing-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-10T10:16:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/10/creativity-is-often-just-about-showing-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> Inspiration is frequently misunderstood. When I was a young writer I looked
 for it in all the wrong places. In my twenties, I lived with my wife in a
 studio apartment just off Washington Square. Somehow I decided that the best
 writing time for me was late at night–I guessed that was when the muses
 would be running wild and delivering intoxicating poetic secrets. Perhaps I
 got this impression from Thelonious Monk’s ‘Round about Midnight” which I
 played over and over–it was so hauntingly beautiful and sad. In those days,
 after a late heavy dinner with a couple of beers topped off by more than a
 few drags of weed, I took my yellow legal pad into the chilly unsightly
 stairwell across from my front door and got ready to write the great
 American novel. Ugh, wrong move, Waitz. I recall sitting in the stairwell
 waiting for inspiration to strike until I was dozing off or feeling too
 cold. Some evenings when my wife was off taking classes at N.Y.U., for
 inspiration I maxed out the hifi with Ornette Coleman or John Coltrane
 blasting pure madness solos while I tried to compose my delicate pages.
 Wrong. Wrong. All wrong, Waitzkin.</p>

<p> Now, many years later, when I’m working on a book I write everyday except
 Sunday, when I watch football or go to the country with my wife. This routine
 has settled deeply inside. It gives me confidence. I’ve learned that pages
 will come if I go to my quiet office and stick with my routine. Back in the
 younger days, the unsightly stairwell seemed cool, but not now. I could never
 do my best work after a heavy meal or with the music blasting. It would be a
 distraction–an energy robber.</p></blockquote>

<p>That&#8217;s an excerpt from <a href="http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2013/03/24/the-alchemy-of-writing-tips-from-a-non-fiction-and-fiction-pro/">an interview between Tim Ferris and Fred Waitzkin</a>
with Waitzkin discussing inspiration.</p>

<p>Inspiration is often seen as a kind of &#8220;eureka moment&#8221; where great ideas
suddenly materialize. We view inspiration as an instantaneous event.
Inspiration either happens, or it doesn&#8217;t.</p>

<p>This couldn&#8217;t be further from the truth.</p>

<p>The examples are everywhere. If you look at Mark Zuckerberg, Facebook was not
his only success. Facebook was a culmination of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg#Software_developer">years of software development</a>
throughout his teens. He didn&#8217;t randomly realize the power of the Internet and
then decide to build a social network. He spent years on the Internet before
realizing its potential uses. He spent years programming before building
something great.</p>

<p>If you dislike anecdotal evidence (for good reasons!), there is <em>empirical
evidence</em> to support this claim. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conscientiousness#Behavior">Conscientousness has positive effects on life outcomes</a>
according to a variety of different measurements. The desire for excellence and
a willingness to do hard work is a key factor in determining success.</p>

<p>Effectively, our intuitive notions of inspiration may just be a byproduct of
our inability to consciously trace the origins of our best ideas. Instead of
attempting to replicate the actions that led us to good ideas, we are caught in
trying to replicate the <em>situations</em> that led us to good ideas. This is
reflected by the fundamental attribution error: when we see other people&#8217;s
successes, we associate the results with a property of the people themselves, but when we
see our own successes, we associate the results with the situation we are in.</p>

<p>The hardest part of creative work is <em>starting</em> and <em>continuing</em> the work.
&#8220;Inspiration&#8221; is the easy part.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What causes burnout?]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/09/what-causes-burnout/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T18:25:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/09/what-causes-burnout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed an <a href="http://iamnotaprogrammer.com/Burnout-is-caused-by-resentment.html#comment-478842490">excellent comment on Marissa Mayer&#8217;s blog</a>
about the nature of burnout.</p>

<blockquote><p>Burnout is caused when you repeatedly make large amounts of sacrifice and or
effort into high-risk problems that fail.  It&#8217;s the result of a negative
prediction error in the nucleus accumbens.  You effectively condition your
brain to associate work with failure.</p>

<p>Subconsciously, then eventually, consciously, you wonder if it&#8217;s worth it.
The best way to prevent burnout is to follow up a serious failure with doing
small things that you know are going to work.</p></blockquote>

<p>Many times, burnout is attributed to working too hard. Though this is certainly
a cause, it is important to understand that the burnout is more likely to occur
if the work isn&#8217;t <em>rewarded</em> in a satisfying way.</p>

<p>This is the reason why people are willing to sink hundreds of hours into video
games doing seemingly boring tasks like mining for gold. The behavior gets
rewarded within the game <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement#Schedules">according to a schedule</a>
that optimizes for addiction. The banality of the task is offset by the
instantaneous rewards provided by the system.</p>

<p>As described in the comment, the key to avoiding burnout is not necessarily
just to reduce workload. The key to avoiding burnout appears to be the use of
small guaranteed successes as a way to offset the cognitive impact of large
failures.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rabbits and Lemonade]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/08/rabbits-and-lemonade/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T20:45:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/08/rabbits-and-lemonade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No Walrus.<br/>
No Queen of Hearts.<br/>
Not even the Mad Hatter.</p>

<p>Adventures disappeared from my mind&#8230;</p>

<p>Even still, I find a question that mattered:<br/>
Where are all of the walls in which I am confined<br/>
And what machine shall I build to ensure that they&#8217;re shattered?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security and Privacy]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/07/security-and-privacy/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T20:11:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/07/security-and-privacy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.schneier.com/">Bruce Schneier&#8217;s Blog</a> is an ecellent web site to
read, especially if you are interested in issues related to security. Although
a lot of his writing can be very technical, there are a few of his essays that
make complex ideas easier to understand. One of my favorite posts from his blog
is <a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2008/01/security_vs_pri.html">Security vs. Privacy</a>, an
analysis of the false dilemma that is often constructed between national
security and individual privacy.</p>

<p>Not all security measures need to violate privacy, and not all violations of
privacy lead to increased levels of security. An attempt to frame security and
privacy as two opposing forces is misinformed at its best and pernicious at its
worst.</p>

<p>To put it a step further, invasions of privacy are often attempts to profile
people. By establishing patterns that describe a <em>typical terrorist</em>, we can
narrow our searches and focus on people who actually exhibit behavior that
resembles known terrorists. The standard argument is, &#8220;if you have nothing to
hide, why should you care?&#8221;</p>

<p>Although privacy is important for its own sake, using personal information like
Internet usage or private emails to find suspected terrorists is <em>not a very
good idea</em>. A person with the desire to execute a complex terror plot will
probably not send vital information over an unencrypted channel. Unless the
NSA can outsmart <a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GPG</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security">TLS</a>,
the invasions of privacy will only foil terror plots conducted by
unsophisticated groups. The benefits associated with sacrifices of privacy
would be marginal at best. The end result will be an ocean of information
available to government agencies about
ordinary people without the knowledge to protect themselves.</p>

<p>This is the same reason why pilots have to go through airport security. Even
though a pilot can crash the plane, the security concern is not about the
potential damage a pilot can cause. The security concern is about whether the
pilot <em>is actually a pilot</em>. When designing a security system, the security of
the whole system is only as good as the weakest link. If pilots don&#8217;t have to go
through ordinary security lines, a terrorist would only need a pilot&#8217;s uniform
and badge to go through security undetected.</p>

<p>Likewise, if we use people&#8217;s private information, whether it&#8217;s emails or Facebook
activity, we should be careful not to create a tiered security system. If a
potential terrorist only needs to act normal on Facebook in order to avoid
the government&#8217;s attention, monitoring Facebook accounts will not actually
provide more security.</p>

<p>Security is always a matter of cost and benefit, but privacy is rarely an
effective price to pay.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coursera Machine Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/06/coursera-machine-learning/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T23:06:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/06/coursera-machine-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m two weeks into the <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/ml">Stanford Machine Learning course</a>
taught by Andrew Ng through Coursera.</p>

<p>The class is excellent, and I&#8217;m having a great time going through the material.
Coursera&#8217;s platform not only makes it really easy to watch the lectures, but
the material in the course is taught really well.</p>

<p>Overall, the experience has been overwhelmingly positive.</p>

<p>There are two types of assignments in the class: lecture review questions and
programming exercises. The lecture review questions are multiple choice
questions you complete online, and the programming exercises are
automatically-graded code exercises that focus on Octave.</p>

<p>So far, the material has been relatively simple, and the course has only
covered a brief introduction to the topic of Machine Learning as well as linear
regression with a single or multiple variables. The Octave programming language
has also been introduced, but the course is still progressing quite well.</p>

<p>The high quality of the course and the amazing price tag (free!) seem to be
signalling pretty big changes in education coming soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Personal MBA]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/05/the-personal-mba/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-05T21:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/05/the-personal-mba</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://personalmba.com/">The Personal MBA</a> by Josh Kaufman is probably one of
the best business books I&#8217;ve read. I usually don&#8217;t enjoy reading business
books, but Kaufman does an excellent job of being precise and concise in his
explanations of terminology and strategy.</p>

<p>In short, a business is a repeatable process that:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>creates or provides something of value that</li>
<li>other people want or need</li>
<li>at a price they’re willing to pay, in a way that</li>
<li>satisfies the purchaser’s needs and expectations and</li>
<li>provides the business sufficient revenue to make it worthwhile for the owners to continue operation.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>As Kaufman says, everything else is a hobby.</p>

<p>Although <a href="http://sivers.org/book/PersonalMBA">Derek Sivers&#8217; review</a> of the book
is a very good summary, the book itself is a must-read for anyone who wants to
start a business.</p>

<p>A few key takeaways:</p>

<ul>
<li>Test everything. Any assumption that is untested should be questioned unless
there is external evidence (e.g. science) that validates the assumption.</li>
<li>Business is all about creating value and extracting a portion of the value
that is created.</li>
<li>There are two things your business does: things that provide value and waste.</li>
<li>We are inherently biased towards the things we create. External validation is
crucial.</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t delay a launch in search of perfection, but iterate towards it over
time.</li>
<li>Measure the lifetime value of a customer and the cost of acquiring a customer
through different channels. Once these variables are measured, and the cost
of acquiring a customer is less than the lifetime value, profits will be easy
to increase.</li>
<li>Test prices. Higher prices are usually not as bad as you may think.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Actually Change Your Mind]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/04/how-to-actually-change-your-mind/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-04T23:03:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/04/how-to-actually-change-your-mind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most valuable things I have ever read is the
<a href="http://lesswrong.com/">LessWrong</a> sequence
<a href="http://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/How_To_Actually_Change_Your_Mind">How To Actually Change Your Mind</a>.</p>

<p>I recommend it without hesitation to anyone who hasn&#8217;t already read it.</p>

<p>Here are some gems:</p>

<blockquote><p>When you see people insisting that no amount of money whatsoever is worth a
single human life, and then driving an extra mile to save $10; or when you
see people insisting that no amount of money is worth a decrement of health,
and then choosing the cheapest health insurance available; then you don&#8217;t
think that their protestations reveal some deep truth about incommensurable
utilities.</p>

<p>In the West, there is a saying: &#8220;The squaky wheel gets the grease.&#8221; In Japan,
the corresponding saying runs: &#8220;The nail that sticks up gets hammered down.&#8221;</p>

<p>I believe there was a lawsuit where someone alleged that the draft lottery
was unfair, because the slips with names on them were not being mixed
thoroughly enough; and the judge replied, &#8220;To whom is it unfair?&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;If we cannot learn to take joy in the merely real, our lives will be empty
indeed.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>The entire sequence is very long, but also worth reading through. It is the
kind of thing that changes the way you think, and it includes numerous
interesting footnotes and citations that provide an endless rabbit hole of
thought-provoking content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Spring on the Tongariro Crossing]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/03/a-spring-on-the-tongariro-crossing/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T20:42:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/03/a-spring-on-the-tongariro-crossing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://shan.tanu.me/uploads/tongariro.jpg" alt="A Spring on the Tongariro Crossing" /></p>

<p>The above photograph was taken at the Tongariro Alpine Crossing in New Zealand,
and it&#8217;s a picture of a spring near the summit.</p>

<p>The hike up was amazing, and there was even some minor volcanic activity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Practicing Memorizing]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/02/practicing-memorizing/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-02T11:48:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/02/practicing-memorizing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m working on my ability to remember information. Instead of using memory
&#8220;tricks&#8221; like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci">method of loci</a>
or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chunking_%28psychology%29">chunking</a>, I&#8217;m
working on simply using a &#8220;brute force&#8221; approach to storing information in
long term memory using flash cards.</p>

<p>Although this isn&#8217;t the most efficient way to remember information, it&#8217;s the
best way to remember information <em>unintentionally</em>.</p>

<p>The problem with the method of loci and chunking is simple: those techniques
only provide you with access to information within the context of the
technique. The method of loci makes memorizing information very easy, but you
need to focus on visualizing a spatial location to access your memories.
Chunking groups small pieces of information into larger parts, but what if you
need an individual piece at a random time?</p>

<p>The problem with a lot of memory techniques is that they don&#8217;t address the main
issue with memory: when is it useful to know the information? Chunking and the
method of loci are useful for memorizing a speech or for situations when you
know in advance that you will need a piece of information.</p>

<p>What if I need information, but I can&#8217;t predict when or how that need will
arise?</p>

<p>The best way, in that situation, is to create as many associations with
related things as possible. As a result, I&#8217;m giving a few different flash card
tools a try. With these tools, I&#8217;m attempting to memorize maps of the world,
vocabulary words, historical events, and animal species. To make the process as
effective as possible, I&#8217;m working on creating a set of images from Flickr
corresponding to each of the words, and the flash cards will have multiple
&#8220;definitions&#8221; that can point to a single word.</p>

<p>So far, I&#8217;ve enjoyed using the following tools:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://ankisrs.net/">Anki</a> - a downloadable tool that tracks the intervals
between correct and incorrect recall to maximize the probability of
successfully storing a flash card in long term memory</li>
<li><a href="http://quizlet.com/">Quizlet</a> - a web-based social tool with thousands of
existing sets of flash cards that are ripe for memorizing and learning</li>
<li><a href="http://www.memrise.com/">Memrise</a> - a newer and sleeker web-based tool with
fewer flash cards available to study, but incorporates gamification and
tracking of accuracy to maximize recall</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Books I'm Reading]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/01/books-im-reading/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T21:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/01/books-im-reading</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some books that I&#8217;m reading right now, and they&#8217;re all fantastic.</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Dune</em> by Frank Herbert - this is a science fiction book involving
intergalactic politics and complicated plots</li>
<li><em>Thinking Fast and Slow</em> by Daniel Kahneman - this is a nonfiction book
written by a Nobel Prize winner in economics about how we make sense of
information and form conclusions</li>
<li><em>Titan</em> by Ron Chernow - this is a biography of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. that
is unfortunately dry at times, but has some great stories</li>
</ul>


<p>I&#8217;m trying to get in the habit of reviewing books, so this is my way of holding
myself accountable: I&#8217;ll post reviews by the end of May.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salman Rushdie]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/29/salman-rushdie/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-29T20:41:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/29/salman-rushdie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Salman Rushdie is an amazing author. His books produce magic in ways that I
can&#8217;t explain in a blog post.</p>

<p>I particularly enjoyed this talk:</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315"
src="http://shan.tanu.me//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/owerxb8rSPo" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>And I particularly enjoy this quote from <em>Midnight&#8217;s Children</em>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Who what am I? My answer: I am the sum total of everything that went before
me, of all I have been seen done, of everything done-to-me. I am everyone
everything whose being-in-the-world affected was affected by mine. I am
anything that happens after I&#8217;ve gone which would not have happened if I had
not come. Nor am I particularly exceptional in this matter; each &#8220;I,&#8221; every
one of the now-six-hundred-million-plus of us, contains a similar multitude.
I repeat for the last time: to understand me, you&#8217;ll have to swallow a world.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Problems in Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/12/problems-in-education/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T21:24:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/12/problems-in-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The specific project I was evaluating had only gotten $800,000 out of the
maximum $2m. Its strategy was to purchase the male students iPod Touches, the
female students makeovers, manicures, and pedicures at a local beauty parlor,
and all students were offered an additional iPod Touch or Makeover,
respectively, if they passed the exam at the end of the current year. The
grant proposal had specifically listed these actions as being the goal of the
proposal. If the iPods and makeovers were purchased, that constituted
success.</p></blockquote>

<p>This was from a LessWrong article about the
<a href="http://lesswrong.com/r/discussion/lw/h5z/problems_in_education/">problems with education</a>.</p>

<p>Although this article outlines the problems with the way funds are distributed
to our schools through grants, it is a problem with human nature.</p>

<p>Once we create a solution to a problem, we judge the success of our endeavours
by the success with which we execute our solution instead of judging based on
the <em>metrics that define the problem</em>.</p>

<p>The short answer: measure everything, and evaluate results based on the
evidence.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Attraction of Fan Fiction]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/11/the-attraction-of-fan-fiction/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T21:12:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/11/the-attraction-of-fan-fiction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished re-reading all of Eliezer Yudkowsky&#8217;s Harry Potter fanfic -
<a href="http://hpmor.com/">Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality</a>. After reading
it again, I have a new appreciation for what Eliezer is attempting.</p>

<p>Writing fan fiction based on a series as popular as Harry Potter allows Eliezer
to construct a new world from existing parts. Instead of having to spend
enormous amounts of time establishing the histories and personalities of his
characters, he can focus only on the parts that are <em>different</em> from the
original work. It is through these differences that Eliezer is able to explain
seemingly-complex concepts involving Bayesian Rationality, quantum mechanics,
cognitive biases, and psychology.</p>

<p>The references to science seem forced at times, but the underlying story is
gripping in a way that is very different from J.K. Rowling&#8217;s writing. Eliezer
has elevated the art of fan fiction to a different level - instead of just
constructing a story that extends the original, he constructs a story that
transcends it.</p>

<p>Give it a shot. It&#8217;s worth reading.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Quotes from Musashi]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/10/some-quotes-from-musashi/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-10T23:19:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/10/some-quotes-from-musashi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished re-reading <em>Musashi</em> by Eiji Yoshikawa. It is possibly my
favorite book, and I will write a more comprehensive book review another time.
For now, I just wanted to share a few quotes that I thought were golden.</p>

<p>If you are striving to improve yourself to a point of perfection, read
<em>Musashi</em>. If you are interested in martial arts, read <em>Musashi</em>. If you enjoy
reading books, read <em>Musashi</em>. It is a gripping story that is written with wit
and wisdom.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Ah, even I&#8217;m beginning to think priests are crazy. Everywhere they go, they
meet no one but people rushing toward hell.&#8221;</p>

<p>I am not so distant from the gods and the universe. I can touch them with the
three-foot sword I carry. But not so long as I feel there is a distinction
between nature and humankind. Not so long as I remain distant from the realm
of the true expert, the fully developed man.&#8221;</p>

<p>You seem to be under the misconception that if you perform one brave deed,
that alone makes you a samurai. Well it doesn&#8217;t! you let that one act of
loyalty convince you of your righteousness. The more convinced you became,
the more harm you caused yourself and everyone else.</p></blockquote>

<p>In Musashi&#8217;s own (non-fiction) <em>Book of Five Rings</em>, he says:</p>

<blockquote><p>When I reached thirty I looked back on my past. The previous victories were
not due to my having mastered strategy. Perhaps it was natural ability, or
the order of heaven, or that other schools&#8217; strategy was inferior. After that
I studied morning and evening searching for the principle, and came to
realise the Way of strategy when I was fifty. Since then I have lived without
following any particular Way. Thus with the virtue of strategy I practise
many arts and abilities — all things with no teacher. To write this book I
did not use the law of Buddha or the teachings of Confucius, neither old war
chronicles nor books on martial tactics. I take up my brush to explain the
true spirit of this Ichi school as it is mirrored in the Way of heaven and
Kwannon. The time is the night of the tenth day of the tenth month, at the
hour of the tiger.</p></blockquote>

<p>I still feel like I haven&#8217;t encapsulated the essence of it all. I&#8217;ll try again
tomorrow&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ancient World Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/09/the-ancient-world-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T22:23:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/09/the-ancient-world-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just recently stubmled across <a href="http://ancientworldpodcast.blogspot.com/">The Ancient World</a>,
a podcast about ancient civilizations.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m beginning to really enjoy learning about history through audio, and this
podcast brilliantly describes Ancient Mesopotamia really well, and it is still
being updated with new episodes!</p>

<p>There are two (no longer updated) podcasts that are still worth listening to:
<a href="http://www.dancarlin.com/disp.php/hh">Hardcore History</a> and
<a href="http://thehistoryofrome.typepad.com/">The History of Rome</a>.</p>

<p>Learning about history can be fascinating for a simple (and trite) reason: past
events often resemble our present predicaments.</p>

<p>One such example is the life of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucius_Cornelius_Sulla">Lucius Cornelius Sulla</a>,
a general in Rome over 2,000 years ago.</p>

<p>Sulla was one of the first to break the rules of the constitution of the Roman
Republic in an effort to <em>preserve the values of the constitution</em>.</p>

<p>Sound familiar?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moonwalking with Einstein]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/08/moonwalking-with-einstein/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T10:53:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/08/moonwalking-with-einstein</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Moonwalking with Einstein</em> by Joshua Foer is an excellent book. Although you
can watch his TED talk to get a quick summary of the book&#8217;s main ideas, I would
highly recommend reading the book.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://shan.tanu.me//www.youtube.com/embed/U6PoUg7jXsA"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The book details his journey from being an ordinary journalist to a memory
champion - he went from having average memory to being able to memorize
thousand-digit numbers with ease. The most startling part of the entire book:
anyone can perform the same tricks with an average memory.</p>

<p>The memory techniques definitely seem like <em>tricks</em>, but they are very
effective, and date back to Cicero&#8217;s speeches in the Roman Senate.</p>

<p>Although the specific techniques, like using spatial memory to remember
different details, are interesting, there is another profound aspect to the
book that cannot be overstated: simply because something appears to be
extraordinary does not mean you have to be extraordinary to do it. At first
glance, the ability to memorize thousands of random digits seems like it would
require <em>genius</em>, when it truly just requires focus and practice.</p>

<p>If there is one important lesson to gain from the book, it is that focus and
deliberate practice can produce seemingly superhuman results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/07/surely-youre-joking-mr-feynman/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-07T09:02:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/07/surely-youre-joking-mr-feynman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Surely You&#8217;re Joking Mr. Feynman</em> by Richard Feynman is one of the best
autobiographical books I have ever read. The brilliance of the book is its
seeming lack of structure - Feynman simply jumps between different stories
about his life, but the end result is fascinating. Richard Feynman is possibly
one of the most interesting people to have lived, and this book is good
evidence for that.</p>

<blockquote><p>The electron is a theory we use; it is so useful in understanding the way
nature works that we can almost call it real.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are gems hidden in the book like the above quote. It seems like an
ordinary statement, but hidden inside of it is something really profound:
Feynman is able to put very complex ideas into simple words. He is describing
the difference between the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Map_and_the_Territory">map and the territory</a>
without invoking age-old philosophical discussions. Instead, he uses a
semicolon.</p>

<blockquote><p>I wanted very much to learn to draw, for a reason that I kept to myself: I
wanted to convey an emotion I have about the beauty of the world. It&#8217;s
difficult to describe because it&#8217;s an emotion. It&#8217;s analogous to the feeling
one has in religion that has to do with a god that controls everything in the
whole universe: there&#8217;s a generality aspect that you feel when you think
about how things that appear so different and behave so differently are all
run &#8220;behind the scenes&#8221; by the same organization, the same physical laws.
It&#8217;s an appreciation of the mathematical beauty of nature, of how she works
inside; a realization that the phenomena we see result from the complexity of
the inner workings between atoms; a feeling of how dramatic and wonderful it
is. It&#8217;s a feeling of awe — of scientific awe — which I felt could be
communicated through a drawing to someone who had also had this emotion. It
could remind him, for a moment, of this feeling about the glories of the
universe.</p></blockquote>

<p>Behind Feynman&#8217;s life is a desire to discover the world and bottle it within
his mind. It appears that the book isn&#8217;t just intended as a way to store his
memories. Instead, he closes the novel with a speech he wrote encouraging
students to find environments in which their curiosity can flourish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Phone]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/05/facebook-phone/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T09:02:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/05/facebook-phone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most exciting things about Facebook Home is that Facebook is
releasing a phone in partnership with HTC.</p>

<p>Although I don’t personally use a smart phone, it is fascinating to think about
the change this could bring.</p>

<p>SMS used to be a big deal before the iPhone. It’s only very recently that
social networking has taken over communication, although SMS is still used for
communication that needs to be instant.</p>

<p>The key question for the future: how much will the lines between phone calls,
SMS, and Facebook messaging blur? How long will it take before Facebook
establishes itself as an identity on the same level as a phone number?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Tutorial on Negotiation]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/03/a-tutorial-on-negotiation/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-03T22:17:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/03/a-tutorial-on-negotiation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Planet Money is an excellent podcast, and there was an episode a few months ago when <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/money/2012/12/21/167802325/episode-425-an-fbi-hostage-negotiator-buys-a-car">a hostage negotiator bought a car</a>.</p>

<p>Negotiation is an interesting game of psychology. The episode outlines
different kinds of tactics, like asking for multiple small things individually
to slowly tip the negotiation in your favor. Another tactic was to increase the
&#8220;size of the pie&#8221; by negotiating for things that have more value to you than
the person you are negotiating with.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://shan.tanu.me//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/S0qjK3TWZE8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The above scenario is a little different, but involves similar concepts. It&#8217;s a
variation on the prisoner&#8217;s dilemma. The video is worth a watch, and has
spurred some <a href="http://www.tutor2u.net/blog/index.php/economics/comments/game-show-game-theory">fascinating economic analysis</a>.</p>

<p>In the above variation of the prisoner&#8217;s dilemma, two participants are forced
to choose (without knowing the other person&#8217;s choice) to either split a prize
or steal it. If they both choose to split, they both receive half of the prize.
If one chooses to steal while the other chooses to split, the person who steals
receives the full quantity of the prize. If they both choose to steal, they
lose the entire prize.</p>

<p>The participant in the video changed the rules of the game: instead of playing
the prisoner&#8217;s dilemma, he bent the rules and removed the &#8220;dilemma&#8221; for the
other player.</p>

<p>Sometimes, the best way to negotiate is to step outside of the ordinary
interpretation of the way <em>things are supposed to be</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
