<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: psychology | Shantanu Bala]]></title>
  <link href="http://sbala.org//blog/categories/psychology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sbala.org//"/>
  <updated>2013-05-27T17:09:22+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://sbala.org//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[shantanu@ebookglue.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What causes burnout?]]></title>
    <link href="http://sbala.org//blog/2013/05/09/what-causes-burnout/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T18:25:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://sbala.org//blog/2013/05/09/what-causes-burnout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed an <a href="http://iamnotaprogrammer.com/Burnout-is-caused-by-resentment.html#comment-478842490">excellent comment on Marissa Mayer's blog</a>
about the nature of burnout.</p>

<blockquote><p>Burnout is caused when you repeatedly make large amounts of sacrifice and or
effort into high-risk problems that fail.  It's the result of a negative
prediction error in the nucleus accumbens.  You effectively condition your
brain to associate work with failure.</p>

<p>Subconsciously, then eventually, consciously, you wonder if it's worth it.
The best way to prevent burnout is to follow up a serious failure with doing
small things that you know are going to work.</p></blockquote>

<p>Many times, burnout is attributed to working too hard. Though this is certainly
a cause, it is important to understand that the burnout is more likely to occur
if the work isn't <em>rewarded</em> in a satisfying way.</p>

<p>This is the reason why people are willing to sink hundreds of hours into video
games doing seemingly boring tasks like mining for gold. The behavior gets
rewarded within the game <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement#Schedules">according to a schedule</a>
that optimizes for addiction. The banality of the task is offset by the
instantaneous rewards provided by the system.</p>

<p>As described in the comment, the key to avoiding burnout is not necessarily
just to reduce workload. The key to avoiding burnout appears to be the use of
small guaranteed successes as a way to offset the cognitive impact of large
failures.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
