<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Shantanu Bala]]></title>
  <link href="http://sbala.org//blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sbala.org//"/>
  <updated>2013-05-19T21:03:14+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://sbala.org//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[shantanu@ebookglue.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security and Privacy]]></title>
    <link href="http://sbala.org//blog/2013/05/07/security-and-privacy/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T20:11:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://sbala.org//blog/2013/05/07/security-and-privacy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.schneier.com/">Bruce Schneier's Blog</a> is an ecellent web site to
read, especially if you are interested in issues related to security. Although
a lot of his writing can be very technical, there are a few of his essays that
make complex ideas easier to understand. One of my favorite posts from his blog
is <a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2008/01/security_vs_pri.html">Security vs. Privacy</a>, an
analysis of the false dilemma that is often constructed between national
security and individual privacy.</p>

<p>Not all security measures need to violate privacy, and not all violations of
privacy lead to increased levels of security. An attempt to frame security and
privacy as two opposing forces is misinformed at its best and pernicious at its
worst.</p>

<p>To put it a step further, invasions of privacy are often attempts to profile
people. By establishing patterns that describe a <em>typical terrorist</em>, we can
narrow our searches and focus on people who actually exhibit behavior that
resembles known terrorists. The standard argument is, "if you have nothing to
hide, why should you care?"</p>

<p>Although privacy is important for its own sake, using personal information like
Internet usage or private emails to find suspected terrorists is <em>not a very
good idea</em>. A person with the desire to execute a complex terror plot will
probably not send vital information over an unencrypted channel. Unless the
NSA can outsmart <a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GPG</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security">TLS</a>,
the invasions of privacy will only foil terror plots conducted by
unsophisticated groups. The benefits associated with sacrifices of privacy
would be marginal at best. The end result will be an ocean of information
available to government agencies about
ordinary people without the knowledge to protect themselves.</p>

<p>This is the same reason why pilots have to go through airport security. Even
though a pilot can crash the plane, the security concern is not about the
potential damage a pilot can cause. The security concern is about whether the
pilot <em>is actually a pilot</em>. When designing a security system, the security of
the whole system is only as good as the weakest link. If pilots don't have to go
through ordinary security lines, a terrorist would only need a pilot's uniform
and badge to go through security undetected.</p>

<p>Likewise, if we use people's private information, whether it's emails or Facebook
activity, we should be careful not to create a tiered security system. If a
potential terrorist only needs to act normal on Facebook in order to avoid
the government's attention, monitoring Facebook accounts will not actually
provide more security.</p>

<p>Security is always a matter of cost and benefit, but privacy is rarely an
effective price to pay.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
