<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Shantanu Bala]]></title>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-11T21:21:08+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://shan.tanu.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sh@tanu.me]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Attraction of Fan Fiction]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/11/the-attraction-of-fan-fiction/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T21:12:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/11/the-attraction-of-fan-fiction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished re-reading all of Eliezer Yudkowsky's Harry Potter fanfic -
<a href="http://hpmor.com/">Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality</a>. After reading
it again, I have a new appreciation for what Eliezer is attempting.</p>

<p>Writing fan fiction based on a series as popular as Harry Potter allows Eliezer
to construct a new world from existing parts. Instead of having to spend
enormous amounts of time establishing the histories and personalities of his
characters, he can focus only on the parts that are <em>different</em> from the
original work. It is through these differences that Eliezer is able to explain
seemingly-complex concepts involving Bayesian Rationality, quantum mechanics,
cognitive biases, and psychology.</p>

<p>The references to science seem forced at times, but the underlying story is
gripping in a way that is very different from J.K. Rowling's writing. Eliezer
has elevated the art of fan fiction to a different level - instead of just
constructing a story that extends the original, he constructs a story that
transcends it.</p>

<p>Give it a shot. It's worth reading.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Quotes from Musashi]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/10/some-quotes-from-musashi/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-10T23:19:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/10/some-quotes-from-musashi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished re-reading <em>Musashi</em> by Eiji Yoshikawa. It is possibly my
favorite book, and I will write a more comprehensive book review another time.
For now, I just wanted to share a few quotes that I thought were golden.</p>

<p>If you are striving to improve yourself to a point of perfection, read
<em>Musashi</em>. If you are interested in martial arts, read <em>Musashi</em>. If you enjoy
reading books, read <em>Musashi</em>. It is a gripping story that is written with wit
and wisdom.</p>

<blockquote><p>"Ah, even I'm beginning to think priests are crazy. Everywhere they go, they
meet no one but people rushing toward hell."</p>

<p>I am not so distant from the gods and the universe. I can touch them with the
three-foot sword I carry. But not so long as I feel there is a distinction
between nature and humankind. Not so long as I remain distant from the realm
of the true expert, the fully developed man."</p>

<p>You seem to be under the misconception that if you perform one brave deed,
that alone makes you a samurai. Well it doesn't! you let that one act of
loyalty convince you of your righteousness. The more convinced you became,
the more harm you caused yourself and everyone else.</p></blockquote>

<p>In Musashi's own (non-fiction) <em>Book of Five Rings</em>, he says:</p>

<blockquote><p>When I reached thirty I looked back on my past. The previous victories were
not due to my having mastered strategy. Perhaps it was natural ability, or
the order of heaven, or that other schools' strategy was inferior. After that
I studied morning and evening searching for the principle, and came to
realise the Way of strategy when I was fifty. Since then I have lived without
following any particular Way. Thus with the virtue of strategy I practise
many arts and abilities — all things with no teacher. To write this book I
did not use the law of Buddha or the teachings of Confucius, neither old war
chronicles nor books on martial tactics. I take up my brush to explain the
true spirit of this Ichi school as it is mirrored in the Way of heaven and
Kwannon. The time is the night of the tenth day of the tenth month, at the
hour of the tiger.</p></blockquote>

<p>I still feel like I haven't encapsulated the essence of it all. I'll try again
tomorrow...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moonwalking with Einstein]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/08/moonwalking-with-einstein/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T10:53:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/08/moonwalking-with-einstein</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Moonwalking with Einstein</em> by Joshua Foer is an excellent book. Although you
can watch his TED talk to get a quick summary of the book's main ideas, I would
highly recommend reading the book.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://shan.tanu.me//www.youtube.com/embed/U6PoUg7jXsA"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The book details his journey from being an ordinary journalist to a memory
champion - he went from having average memory to being able to memorize
thousand-digit numbers with ease. The most startling part of the entire book:
anyone can perform the same tricks with an average memory.</p>

<p>The memory techniques definitely seem like <em>tricks</em>, but they are very
effective, and date back to Cicero's speeches in the Roman Senate.</p>

<p>Although the specific techniques, like using spatial memory to remember
different details, are interesting, there is another profound aspect to the
book that cannot be overstated: simply because something appears to be
extraordinary does not mean you have to be extraordinary to do it. At first
glance, the ability to memorize thousands of random digits seems like it would
require <em>genius</em>, when it truly just requires focus and practice.</p>

<p>If there is one important lesson to gain from the book, it is that focus and
deliberate practice can produce seemingly superhuman results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/07/surely-youre-joking-mr-feynman/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-07T09:02:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/04/07/surely-youre-joking-mr-feynman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Surely You're Joking Mr. Feynman</em> by Richard Feynman is one of the best
autobiographical books I have ever read. The brilliance of the book is its
seeming lack of structure - Feynman simply jumps between different stories
about his life, but the end result is fascinating. Richard Feynman is possibly
one of the most interesting people to have lived, and this book is good
evidence for that.</p>

<blockquote><p>The electron is a theory we use; it is so useful in understanding the way
nature works that we can almost call it real.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are gems hidden in the book like the above quote. It seems like an
ordinary statement, but hidden inside of it is something really profound:
Feynman is able to put very complex ideas into simple words. He is describing
the difference between the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Map_and_the_Territory">map and the territory</a>
without invoking age-old philosophical discussions. Instead, he uses a
semicolon.</p>

<blockquote><p>I wanted very much to learn to draw, for a reason that I kept to myself: I
wanted to convey an emotion I have about the beauty of the world. It's
difficult to describe because it's an emotion. It's analogous to the feeling
one has in religion that has to do with a god that controls everything in the
whole universe: there's a generality aspect that you feel when you think
about how things that appear so different and behave so differently are all
run "behind the scenes" by the same organization, the same physical laws.
It's an appreciation of the mathematical beauty of nature, of how she works
inside; a realization that the phenomena we see result from the complexity of
the inner workings between atoms; a feeling of how dramatic and wonderful it
is. It's a feeling of awe — of scientific awe — which I felt could be
communicated through a drawing to someone who had also had this emotion. It
could remind him, for a moment, of this feeling about the glories of the
universe.</p></blockquote>

<p>Behind Feynman's life is a desire to discover the world and bottle it within
his mind. It appears that the book isn't just intended as a way to store his
memories. Instead, he closes the novel with a speech he wrote encouraging
students to find environments in which their curiosity can flourish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
