<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: memory | Shantanu Bala]]></title>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/categories/memory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-15T18:48:07+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://shan.tanu.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shantanu Bala]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[sh@tanu.me]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Practicing Memorizing]]></title>
    <link href="http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/02/practicing-memorizing/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-02T11:48:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://shan.tanu.me/blog/2013/05/02/practicing-memorizing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm working on my ability to remember information. Instead of using memory
"tricks" like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci">method of loci</a>
or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chunking_%28psychology%29">chunking</a>, I'm
working on simply using a "brute force" approach to storing information in
long term memory using flash cards.</p>

<p>Although this isn't the most efficient way to remember information, it's the
best way to remember information <em>unintentionally</em>.</p>

<p>The problem with the method of loci and chunking is simple: those techniques
only provide you with access to information within the context of the
technique. The method of loci makes memorizing information very easy, but you
need to focus on visualizing a spatial location to access your memories.
Chunking groups small pieces of information into larger parts, but what if you
need an individual piece at a random time?</p>

<p>The problem with a lot of memory techniques is that they don't address the main
issue with memory: when is it useful to know the information? Chunking and the
method of loci are useful for memorizing a speech or for situations when you
know in advance that you will need a piece of information.</p>

<p>What if I need information, but I can't predict when or how that need will
arise?</p>

<p>The best way, in that situation, is to create as many associations with
related things as possible. As a result, I'm giving a few different flash card
tools a try. With these tools, I'm attempting to memorize maps of the world,
vocabulary words, historical events, and animal species. To make the process as
effective as possible, I'm working on creating a set of images from Flickr
corresponding to each of the words, and the flash cards will have multiple
"definitions" that can point to a single word.</p>

<p>So far, I've enjoyed using the following tools:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://ankisrs.net/">Anki</a> - a downloadable tool that tracks the intervals
between correct and incorrect recall to maximize the probability of
successfully storing a flash card in long term memory</li>
<li><a href="http://quizlet.com/">Quizlet</a> - a web-based social tool with thousands of
existing sets of flash cards that are ripe for memorizing and learning</li>
<li><a href="http://www.memrise.com/">Memrise</a> - a newer and sleeker web-based tool with
fewer flash cards available to study, but incorporates gamification and
tracking of accuracy to maximize recall</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
